<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True and wonderfull A discourse relating to a strange and monstrous serpent (or dragon) lately discouered, and yet liuing, to the great annoyance and diuers slaughters both of men and cattell, by his strong and violent poyson, in Sussex two miles from Horsam, in a woode called S. Leonards Forrest, and thirtie miles from London, this present month of August. 1614. With the true generation of serpents.</title>
            <author>A. R., fl. 1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840317</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840317</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 857:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True and wonderfull A discourse relating to a strange and monstrous serpent (or dragon) lately discouered, and yet liuing, to the great annoyance and diuers slaughters both of men and cattell, by his strong and violent poyson, in Sussex two miles from Horsam, in a woode called S. Leonards Forrest, and thirtie miles from London, this present month of August. 1614. With the true generation of serpents.</title>
                  <author>A. R., fl. 1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Iohn Trundle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1614]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: A.R.</note>
                  <note>Printed by E. Allde. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-C⁴(-C4).</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dragons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:1"/>
            <p>True and Wonderfull. A Diſcourſe relating a ſtrange and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Serpent (or Dragon) lately diſcouered, and yet liuing, to the great annoyance and diuers ſlaughters both of Men and Cattell, by his ſtrong and violent poyſon, <hi>In</hi> Suſſex <hi>two miles from</hi> Horſam, <hi>in a woode</hi> called S. Leonards Forreſt, and thirtie miles from London, <hi>this preſent month of Auguſt.</hi> 1614. With the true Generation of Serpents.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a fire-breathing dragon facing a crouching cat, next to a man, woman, and dog or cow lying on the ground</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Iohn Trundle.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He iuſt Reward</hi> of him that is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to lie, is, not to be belieu'd when he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the truth: So iuſt an occaſion may ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time bee impos'd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Pamphleting, preſſe, and therefore if we receiue the ſame rewards wee cannot much blame our accuſers, which often fals out ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our forward credulity to but ſeeming true reports, or by falſe Coppies tranſlated from other Languages, which (though we beget not) wee fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and our ſhame little the leſſe. But paſſing by what's paſt, let not our preſent truth bluſh for any former falſhood ſake: The Countrie is neere vs, <hi>Suſſex;</hi> The Time preſent, <hi>Auguſt;</hi> The Subiect, a <hi>Serpent;</hi> ſtrange, yet now a neighbour to vs: and it were more then impudence to forge a lie ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4807:3"/> neere home, that euery man might turne in our throates; belieue it, or reade it not, or reade it (doubting) for I belieue e're thou haſt read this little All, thou wilt not doubt of one, but belieue there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Serpents in <hi>England;</hi> farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>A. R. He that would ſend better newes if he had it.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:3"/>
            <head>True and Wonderfull: A Diſcourſe relating a ſtrange &amp; monſtrous Serpent (or Dragon) lately diſcouered and yet liuing, to the great anoyance (and diuers ſlaughters) both of Men and Cattell, by his ſtrong &amp; violent Poyſon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more</hi> miraculous in na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture as the ſhalow ſearch of humane apprehenſion, then the workes of the diuinitie ſpecified in the Creation, being a worke beautified with diſtinction, order and meaſure, and ſifted from all confuſion: yet if we more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly vnrip the natures and qualities of the creatures, leauing the vnſearchable depth of Gods eſſence beyond the ſhoomakers laſt of capacitie to himſelfe, we ſhall finde that there is ſufficient cauſe for our weake admirations: And though all things were at the firſt created good and ſeruicable to man, becauſe God is not the author of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euill; yet ſince euill ſprung from the ill of <hi>Eue,</hi> many miſeries haue (as his curſſe) falne to man, euen by thoſe creatures which were his companions in Paradice, and made to his great bleſſing and benefit, Inſomuch that the Serpent which firſt was familiar with <hi>Eue,</hi> &amp; ſeruiceable
<pb facs="tcp:4807:4"/> to mans vſe, is now turned a deadly and fatall enemy to all his poſteritie, frighting the earth with monſtrous and prodigious ſhapes: and no doubt, in theſe new and preſaging formes, are ſent to puniſh our new inuentions of ſinne, according to the ſaying of a reuerend Father: <hi>Quia deliquimus in multis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>punimur in multis:</hi> Becauſe we haue offended in many things, we are puniſhed in many.</p>
            <p>But to omit the Sanctuary of vnfurniſht wits, being a fugitiue and tedious circuler queſtions, we will apply our briefe abſtract, to the cauſes and originall of theſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous Creatures, for the vnderſtanding and capacitie of the ſimple; ſeeing, that as a learned man ſaith; that <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eſt per cauſas ſcire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato.</note> The beſt way of knowledge is to know by the cauſes: And firſt of their originall.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is Oraculous and plaine in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that God by his word created all things ſenſible and inſenſible: Fiſhes, Foules, Beaſts, and creeping things, and among them Serpents: But ſince the great worke of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are ingendred either naturally or prodigiouſly: Naturally, as ſaith <hi>Macrobius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob.</note> as in <hi>Egipt</hi> Frogs and Mice, are ingendered by raine and ſhewres, ſo alſo are Serpents: But I am of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> opinion, which alſo <hi>Pliny</hi> confirmeth, that Serpents ariſe not from putrifac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by the naturall act of generation. It is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule, that all Beaſts wanting feet, and hauing long bodies;<note place="margin">Elianus.</note> performe their carnall copulation, by the mutuall imbracing of one another: as Lampreies and Serpents: And it is certaine, that two Serpents in this action, ſéeme to be one body and two heads: for they are ſo indiuiſibly vnited together, and the frame of their body vnapt for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other manner of Copulation.<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Serpents.</note> And although like to Fiſhes, they want floure to elaborate the ſperme, yet haue they two open paſſages wherein lyeth their generatiue ſeed; which being ſpread, procureth their veneriall luſts: which ſeed being ciaculated from the Male, into Cels and
<pb facs="tcp:4807:4"/> receptacles of the Female, it is framed into an Egge, which ſhe hydeth in the earth, a hundreth in a cluſter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the quantitie of a birds Egge: And this is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proceeding of all Serpents, except Vipers, who lay no Egges, but hatch their young ones in their wombe; but for their prodigious generation, as it is rare,<note place="margin">
                  <p>A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that brought forth a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
                  <p>Prodigious dreames of Dragons.</p>
               </note> ſo is it alſo horrible to our nature. It is reported, that when <hi>Lucius Scipio,</hi> and <hi>Caius Norbanus</hi> were Conſuls, that the mother of <hi>Claudius</hi> in <hi>Hytruria,</hi> brought forth a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in ſteade of a Childe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Fauſtina</hi> the Empreſſe dreamed, when ſhe was with childe but very prodigiouſly, that ſhe brought forth two Serpents, and one of them ſeemed to be more fiercer then the other, which proued allegorically true: for <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi> afterwards her youngeſt ſonne was ſo tiranicall and barbarous, that he ſeemed to be borne a prodigie to the deſtruction of mankinde: and thus much for their originall, naturall and prodigious.</p>
            <p>The Iriſh ground is moſt happie,<note place="margin">The Iriſh ground happie.</note> and it ſéemeth leſſe ſinnefull, that are frée from contagion of theſe venomous Creatures: but as it is true, that <hi>Non omnis fert omnia tellus,</hi> Euery ground brings not forth all kind of fruites: for this Land were happie if it were leſſe fertile in theſe contagious kind of Serpents, which I aſcribe not to the nature of the earth, but the ſinfull nature of men.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Phrigia</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia</hi> are many Dragons, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and theſe were as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth in the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low places of the earth: and not onely in forraine and farre remote-countries: but alſo in neighboring and nere adioyning nations:<note place="margin">A Dragon brought to the French King. <hi>Stiria</hi> a Towne in <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </note> and firſt of all there was a Serpent or winged Dragon brought vnto <hi>Francis</hi> the French-King: when he lay at <hi>Sancton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sancton.</note> by a country-man: who had ſlaine the ſame Serpent with a ſpade: <hi>Chiſuen</hi> alſo ſaith that in the yeare of our Lord, 1543 there came many Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents with féete, and winges, neere <hi>Stiria:</hi> who wounded the inhabitants incurably.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:5"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paris</hi> a Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in France <hi>Stumphus.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Cardan</hi> writeth that at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France</hi> hée himſelfe ſaw certaine Serpents with winges: when the riuer <hi>Tiber</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowed the banckes many Serpents were diſcouered.</p>
            <p>As alſo in the time of <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, at what time a Dragon came ouer the Citty after which prodigie inſued a great peſtilence. Now as theſe hidious creatures are hurtfull to man, ſo alſo are they moſt inamored of man: and if there be any truth or veritie to be aſcribed to Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: they haue béen moſt paſſionately affected to man wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and child: which ſhowes that it is a worke of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as a iuſt puniſhment of our ſinnes, to turne their affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble natures to a moſt rauenous and deuouring crueltie,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Elianus.</note>And to inſtance this with examples, <hi>Elianus</hi> reports, that their was one <hi>Iliaua</hi> a <hi>Theſalian</hi> Neatheard, that kept Oxen in <hi>Oſſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dragons in loue with Men.</note> hard by the Fountaine <hi>Hemonius,</hi> that a Dragon fell in loue with, for that his yellow haire, which ſéemed in his amiable colour to reſemble Gold, and often come créeping vnto him like an amorous louer, licking his haire and face ſo gentlie, as the man profeſſing he neuer felt the like.</p>
            <p>The like is reported of <hi>Pindus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Macedo</hi> King of <hi>Emuthia,</hi> who was a man of honeſt diſpoſition and a great Hunter: hauing loſt his company in his woonted ſport in a thick and vnfrequented deſert, met with a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon of great ſtature, who came towards <hi>Pindus:</hi> with the greateſt part of his body except his neck lifted vp: who at the firſt was much amazed at ſo horride a ſpectacle, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remembring himſelfe of certaine birds and pieces of ſacrifices which he had about him, he gaue part to the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and ſo mittigated the furie of the Serpent, who being ſmoothed with theſe guifts, and as it were ouertaken with the liberality of <hi>Pindus,</hi> was ſo inamoured of his liberall nature, that he forſooke his deſert habitation, and followed <hi>Pindus</hi> like an ordinarie Spaniell.</p>
            <p>There was alſo a Dragon the louer of <hi>Artheolis,</hi> as <hi>Plutarche</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> writeth, who came to her euery night and did
<pb facs="tcp:4807:5"/> her no harme, but gently ſliding ouer her playd with her till morning, departing away aſſoone as light appeared, leaſt he ſhould be diſcouered.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it is obſerued that thoſe Serpents are ſo far from doing harme, except by ſome ſupernaturall power deſtinate to our ſeuere puniſhment for our ſinnes, that they haue often béen the preuenting cauſes of ſinne, and inſtruments of preſeruation of many men and women.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Meſſalina</hi> the wife of <hi>Claudius</hi> did ſend certaine men to take away the life of <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero</hi> ſaued by a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</note> who was a Riuall of <hi>Britanicus,</hi> a Dragon appeared out of the earth, terrifying the murderers with ſuch furie, that they ranne away and ſpared <hi>Neroes</hi> life.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports of one <hi>Telephus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suetonius,</hi> Inceſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by a Dragon.</note> who had committed inceſt with his mother, had not a Dragon by diuine prouidence frighted the inceſtudus ſonne, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them aſunder. Therefore ſaith the ſame Author, that <hi>Draconi ſimilis eſt vertus indagatrix, quae diligenter omnia perſcrutatur rimuturque ſtudiociſſime,</hi> that perfect diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; knowledge is allegorically ſaid to be like the Dragon, becauſe it diligently ſearcheth the ſecret crannies of all things, and according to the common prouerbe, thorough the ſmalleſt hole ſpies day light.</p>
            <p>But theſe examples doe not conclude, but that there is a ſecret Antipathie and enmitie betwixt Man kind &amp; theſe Serpentine creatures: who indéed after the relapſe and fal of our firſt Parents, as a curſe from God were marked out for moſt noiſome and infectious creatures to man and the womans ſeed &amp; poſteritie: &amp; therfore I could wiſh that the remedy of this our home bred monſter (which hereafter we ſhall more largely expreſſe) were purged with as much breuity as the contents of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Letter to the Senate, <hi>Veni, vidi, vici:</hi> I came, I ſawe, and I ouercame: <hi>vox Dei,</hi> it were the word God, and not of man: Many are the deplorable dangers writ with a tragicall pen of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hiſtorians, which haue inſued to the ſad inhabitants
<pb facs="tcp:4807:6"/> of many famous places by theſe prodigious Monſters, when the region of <hi>Heluctia</hi> began firſt to be purged from theſe noyſome beaſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gellius.</hi> A murderer fighting with the Dragon.</note> there was a horrible Dragon found néere a Countrey Towne called <hi>Wilfer,</hi> who deſtroyed both men and beaſts by his monſtrous and inſatiate hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, inſomuch that that towne was called <hi>Deidwiler,</hi> that is, a Village of the Wilderneſſe: for all the Inhabitants had forſaken the ſame and fled to other places.</p>
            <p>Alſo there is a memorable Hiſtory of a man in the ſame Towne (which I will rehearſe for the ſtrangeneſſe of the accident) that was baniſhed for man-ſlaughter, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for his pardon to combate with the ſame Dragon, which being granted, with much ioye he was called home, and in the preſence of many people went out to fight with the Dragon, whome hee ſlewe and ouercame with diuine aſſiſtance, where for ioy he lifted vp his ſword imbrued in the Dragons blood in token of victorie, which bloud diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from his ſword, and cauſed him inſtantly to fall down dead. A heauie iudgement of God to puniſh murder in the ſame kind, that he who like <hi>Cyrus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cirus.</note> delighted in blood, ſhould féele the curſe of <hi>Tomiris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diuine Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſlie ſhowne.</note> and bee choaked with bloud. Strange that this man who was pardoned for killing of the Dragon, was killed by the Dragon after the Dragon was ſlaine.</p>
            <p>Thus bloud was the ſinne, becauſe it brought death, and death againe brought blood to bee the reuenger of the firſt, that the bloud of man might be waſhed away by the bloud of man: the bloud of the Dragon being vmpire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt, that I may ſay truely, as the Poet ſaith in another caſe, <hi>Sanguine ſuccreuit, Sanguine finis erit:</hi> as it grew ſo ſhall it end in bloud. One example more, and I will conclude this generall diſcodrſe of Serpents, and come to the particular deſcription of our <hi>Suſſexan</hi> Serpent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:6"/>
            <p>Now to the terror of the póore Inhabitants, breathing forth his noiſome poyſons, whoſe Storie deſerues more lamentable teares and ſpéedie extirpation then the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinges of Oratorie, or Penne and Inke-horne cordiall.<note place="margin">Ariſtotle. Philip <hi>of</hi> Maceden.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To note further the contagion of theſe Creatures by the noyſome euaporation of their noyſome breath. In the dayes of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> and father to the great <hi>Alexander,</hi> whoſe Tutor <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was, there was a way into a mountaine to <hi>Armenia,</hi> ouer which the King had prayed that neuer man might goe that way but hee might die. Wherefore <hi>Socrates</hi> to ſée the effect of the Kings prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſet his Opticke Philoſophicall glaſſe, ſuch as now a daies we vſe to apprehend things farre diſtant plainely viſible, to ſee what was in the way, and preſently he perceiued two Dragons that by their breath infected the Region of the aire. Thus wee ſet the obnoxious nature of theſe Serpents to Mankinde, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in our ſoules beſt meditation receiue their birth, according to the ſaying of holie <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that <hi>Deus exaudit ad penam cum petunt peccatoris fomitem,</hi> that our bleſſings are turned into curſings, and our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-noſters to puniſhments, when we pray <hi>fui ſuis,</hi> and our petitions to predictions, when our Chriſtianity is poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſond with ſinne: and therefore now leauing this Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine circute of this generall diſcourſe, and now come to that particular and lamentable Storie of our yet gréene calamitie, as <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dido,</hi>
               <q>Infandum Regina iubes renouare dolorem.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Miſerie is not without a fatall eccho, whoſe imperfect ſillables in formation thus miſerably redoubles.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4807:7"/>
            <q>Veritas non quaerit angulos.</q>
            <p>Let Truth goe vnmaſk't becauſe her face is vnpainted, plainely and truely then: thus, there is diſcouer'd in our neighbour Countie of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> a ſtrange and monſtrous Serpent (a thing moſt noyſome and dreadfull to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants adioyning, and may with pious compaſſion let in remorſe at our eares, to haue a fellow feeling of our neighbours miſerie, ſtill remembring this, that ſinne puls downe puniſhment, and yet there were in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as great ſinnes as thoſe on whome <hi>The Tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 13.</note> if we ſearch our owne boſomes 'tis to be fear'd there will bee found both cauſe and effect, Sinne and Serpent, but leauing our morrall Serpents, let vs returne to the deſcription of our Hiſtoricall one.</p>
            <p>This Serpent (or Dragon as ſome call it) is reputed to be nine foote or rather more in length, and ſhap't almoſt in the forme of an Axeltrée of a Cart, a quantity of thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the middeſt, and ſomewhat ſmaller at both ends, The former part which he ſhootes forth (as a necke) is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be an elle long, with a white ring (as it were) of ſcales about it, The ſcales along his backe ſéemes to bée blackiſh, and ſo much as is deſcoured vnder his bellie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be red, for I ſpeake of no nearer deſcription then of a reaſonable ocular diſtance, for comming too neare it, hath already béene too dearely payd for, as you ſhall heare hereafter.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe diſcouered to haue large féete, but the eye may bee there deceaued, for ſome ſuppoſe that Serpents haue no féete, but glide vppon certaine ribbes and ſcales which both defend him from the vpper part of his throat vnto the lower part of his bellie, and alſo cauſe them to moue much more the faſter, for ſo doth this by firſt draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together &amp; then ſhooting forth, rids way (as we call it) as faſt as a man can run. It is of countenance very proud
<pb facs="tcp:4807:7"/> and at the ſight or hearing of men or Cattell, will raiſe his necke vpright, and ſéeme to liſten and looke about with great arrogancy: There are likewiſe on either ſide of it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer'd two great bunches ſo big as a large foote-ball, and (as ſome thinke) will in time grow to wings, but God (I hope) in their and our aſſiſtance will ſo inſtruct and defend vs that hée ſhall bée deſtroy'd before hee growe ſo fledge.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a fire-breathing dragon facing a crouching cat, next to a man, woman, and dog or cow lying on the ground</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>IN <hi>Suſſex</hi> there is a pretty Market Towne cal'd <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> neare vnto it a Forreſt cal'd S. <hi>Leonards</hi> Forreſt, and there in a vaſt and vnfrequented place, heathie, vaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, full of vnholeſome ſhades, and ouer-growne hollowes it is thought to bee bred, but whereſoeuer bred, certaine and too true it is that there it yet liues, ſo within thrée or foure miles compaſſe are his vſuall haunts, oftentimes at a place cal'd <hi>Faygate,</hi> and he hath béen ſéene within halfe a mile of <hi>Horſam,</hi> a wonder no doubt moſt terrible and noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the Inhabitants thereabouts, there is alwaies in his tracke or path left a glutinous and filmie matter (as by a ſmal ſimilitude we may perceiue in a ſnailes) which is very corrupt and offenſiue to the ſcent, inſomuch that they perceiue the aire to bée putrified withall, which muſt néedes be very dangerous, for though the corruption of it cannot ſtrike the outward part of a man, vnleſſe heated into his blood, yet by receauing of it in at any of our brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Organs, (the Mouth or Noſe) it is by authority of all Authors (writing in that kind) mortall and deadly, as one thus ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:4807:8"/>
               <q>Noxia ſerpentum eſt admixto ſanguine pectis.<note place="margin">Lucanus.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is this Serpent (in my opinion) litterall to be receiued, as when it ſhall pleaſe God that he ſhall bee deſtroyed, that then it may bee preſentlie forgotten, but rather to be fear'd as an Eclips or fearefull Comet, whoſe prodigious effects do alwaies follow, for wee know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our Countrie being temperate, &amp; rather more colde then hot, doth not naturally breede them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that it is ſent amongſt vs to giue vs warning of ſome Serpentine ſinnes that liue amongſt vs, which will (without penitent preuention and conſtant amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) deſtroy vs faſter and farther, then this Serpent doth or can:<note place="margin">Holendſhed.</note> wee may reade in our Engliſh Chronicle of the prodegie in the three and twentith yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Third, and in the yeare of our redemption 1349.</p>
            <p>In Oxford-ſhire neere a place cal'd <hi>Chippingnorton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Chip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingnorton</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi>-ſhire.</note> there was a Serpent was found with two faces and two heads like women, the one hauing the ſhape of the new Perewig and attire of that time, and another in the faſhion of the old attire, and it had alſo wings after the manner of our Rere-Mice or Bats: this was a dreadfull aparition no doubt, and it is to be doubted that wee are not ſhort of that ſinne of new-fangled Tyres now: nay, doe wee not lay it in deeper coulers, and lay on painting too, which perhaps they had not? may we not feare ſuch another Serpents appearance, or rather be blaſted without the warning peece: it were ſo much the happier if wee were ſure of warning: and certainlie it may thence be gathered, that ſinne was then corrected and amended: for not many ages ſince
<pb facs="tcp:4807:9"/> our faſhions were all plaine and decent, yet ſafely (I ſuppoſe) wee may conclude of that mutable ſinne of head-tyring (which hath faſter new formes, and more number then <hi>Hydra</hi> had heads) as ſometime <hi>Seneca</hi> did of couetouſnes,
<q>Etiam fuerint Antiqui.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſpeaking of couetouſnes, extortions, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie and the like, &amp; what ſin may this prodigious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent be applyed more aptlie to them, that poyſonous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Serpentine ſon of couetouſnes: Let theſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants, but looke vpon this Dragon, and they ſhall as apparantly behold themſelues in it as in thoſe times aforeſaid the woman did in the Perewig-Serpents, they encloſe grounds where the true owner, dare not ſet foote in, on paine of their remaining eſtates: ſo doth this Serpent, for none dare approach his abidings, (though none of his owne) but tis the danger of their liues, hee poyſons foure rod from him, and there the Miſer exceedes the Serpent, for hee poyſons many acres diſtant: The Serpent deuours poore mens cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, ſo doth the couetous wretch, both cattell, and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, goods, houſes and all, his ſcales of defence are ſaid to be blacke and reddiſh, and doth it not reſemble the Inke &amp; Waxe, wherein gentlemens lands are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagde, which afterwards turnes offenſiue to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? his necke is long to ouerlooke much, and doth not the Miſer ſo? Tis ſaid likewiſe, to prey vpon Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and doe wee not in this age of ours call thoſe fillie men that fall into their ſnares, Connies? and the poore Maſtiffes that were poyſond, may they not bee properly figur'd by poore mens curſſes bark't out and
<pb facs="tcp:4807:9"/> ſent againſt them? but alas, they mooue them not, but are beaten downe and poyſon'd with their ſtronger venome.</p>
            <p>And laſtly (if they change not the coppy of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine condition) they will leaue behind them at their returne from this world ſuch as the tracke of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent is, when he ſhifts his ground, a ſtench and vnhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſteame: neither the ſweet odour of poore mens prayers, nor the happie farewell of a bleſſed memorie, their farewels will bee both a like, good for the world when they are both gone out of it.</p>
            <q>Auarus niſi cum moritur, nil rectè facit.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Might I not goe further and apply this Serpent to the ſtinging tongues of calumnious backe-biters and ſlanderers? doe not their breaths often poiſon the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and good names of honeſt men and women? let them liſten to this larum-bell too.</p>
            <p>What if I added Drunkards, is there not a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome trackt left after them whereſoeuer they goe? nay, doe they not dailie throw forth their venome? vomites not onely in the fields, but in the ſtréetes, yea, the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nay, their verie friends boſomes are often made the receptacles of their ore-charged ſtomackes.</p>
            <p>Me thinkes in two words more I could heere aptlie applie this Serpent to the moſt common kind of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (I doe not meane the Common-wealth, but the common pouerty rather) to the Serpentine ſiſterhoode of Brotherly, the diſeaſed ſtrumpetrie of the Suburbes: (oh that the Cittie were not frée of, but frée from that Companie:) is not our Serpent diſciphered by a white Ring about his necke? How thinke you when you ſée
<pb facs="tcp:4807:10"/> onely a white Tiffanie about the necke of one of thoſe tugging Gally-ſlaues of Damnation, and all the reſt poiſon? May they not make themſelues readie by loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into this mirror? I dare goe no further in applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and booteleſſe it were vnleſſe I knew how to kill the Serpent.</p>
            <p>But now I will ſet forth two notable examples, the one of a Dragon, the other of a Dog, and the rather I ſéeke to ſet them out, that the wicked thereby may know what they themſelues are, when bruite beaſts ſhall ſet them all to ſchoole.</p>
            <p>There was a man (as <hi>Plinie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> writeth) which foſtered vp a young Dragon,<note place="margin">Thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of a Dragon to his Maſter.</note> who ſéeing the ſame beaſt to waxe wonderfull great, feared to keepe his Dragon any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger within his houſe, and therefore he put him out into a wilde Forreſt. It happened afterward that the ſame man trauailing on his iourney through the Forreſt, was beſet with théeues. And now béeing in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and looking for no other end but death, made (as loath to depart) a great ſhowte and an out-crie: ſtraight vpon whoſe noiſe, and at the knowledge of his voice, the Dragon came to him in all the haſt poſſible. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the théeues being greatly affraid, ran cleane away to ſaue themſelues harmeleſſe. Then the Dragon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted his Maiſter ſafe out of the danger homewards, and returned to the Forreſt againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of a Dog to his Maiſter.</note>The Dog of the Romane <hi>Fuluius</hi> is more wonderful. This <hi>Fuluius</hi> trauailing by the way, was ſlaine with ſlaues that lay in waite for him. His Dogge ſéeing his Maſter dead, laye by him for the ſpace of two daies. Whereuppon when the man was miſſing, and ſearch made for him: they found him dead, with his Dog ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by him. Some maruailing to ſée the Dog lye there
<pb facs="tcp:4807:10"/> by his dead Maiſter, ſtroke him, and would haue driuen him from the dead corſe, and could not: ſome ſéeing ſuch kindneſſe in the Dogge, and pittying him that he ſhould lye there without meat two or thrée daies before: caſt him a piece of fleſh, wherevpon the Dog ſtraight carried the meat to his Maiſters mouth, and would not eate any whit himſelfe, though he had forborne meat ſo long before. And laſt of all, when this dead body ſhould be caſt into the riuer, (according to the manner of the Romaines) the Dog leapt in after, and holding vp his Maiſter ſo long as he could, did chooſe rather to die with him, then to liue without him.</p>
            <p>I would with my concluſion I could haue concluded with the death of this terrible and noiſome Creature, and that (from that generall good to our Countrie) I might haue return'd into euery mans particular boſome to haue deſtroy'd the home-bred Serpents, which are indéed rather our <hi>Penates</hi> or houſhold Gods, then any annoyance to vs, for 'tis our miſerable eſtate (heauen reuert it) rather to adore then abhorre our ſins and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.<note place="margin">Reuelat.</note> 
               <hi>The Dragons taile hath drawen after it moſt part of the ſtars of Heauen:</hi> as reuerend <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, hat, <hi>Magnitudo penarum, facit multitudo peccatorum,</hi> from the monſters of our ſinnes, the monſters of our puniſhment increaſeth.</p>
            <closer>Theſe perſons whoſe names are herevnder prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, haue ſeene this Serpent, beſides diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as the Carrier of Horſam, who lieth at the white Horſe in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> can certifie the truth of all.
<signed>Iohn Steele, Chriſtopher Holder, And a widdow woman dwelling nere <hi>Faygate.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
